Guide to the Alumni Association Records 1888-2008
Oregon State University Libraries, University Archives
Alumni Association Records
1888-2008
1910-1998
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections & Archives Research Center University Archives 121 The Valley Library Oregon State University Corvallis, OR 97331-4501 Phone: 541-737-2165 Email: archives@oregonstate.edu Web: http://osulibrary.oregonstate.edu/archives
RG 035
Oregon State University. Alumni Association.
12.5 cubic feet, including 1000 photographs 19 boxes, including 6 oversize boxes
13 microfilm reels
The Alumni Association Records document the alumni of Oregon State University and the Association's administration, programs and activities, and publications. An alumni organization was established at Corvallis College (now Oregon State University) in 1873.
Historical Note:
The Alumni Association was founded in February 1873 and the first permananent officers were chosen in June of that year: Hugh M. Finley, President; George F. Burkhart, Vice President; W.F. Herrin, Secretary; and Oscar L. Ison, Treasurer. A list of "Alumni et Alumnae" and current addresses was included in each edition of the college catalogue. In 1914 a formal constitution was adopted that provided for a five-member board. E.B. Lemon became the first regular alumni secretary in 1915 and started the alumni magazine, the OAC Alumnus. In 1926, the alumni magazine became the Oregon State Monthly; it was renamed the Oregon Stater in 1940 and has retained that title since.
In 1929, the alumni office was moved from the Commerce Building to the newly completed Memorial Union. The CH2M Hill Alumni Center was completed on campus in 1997; it was built as a conference and meeting center and as the home of OSU Alumni Association events and administrative offices.
The Alumni Association has been lead by several Alumni Secretaries and Executive Directors, including Godfrey Hoerner, 1919-1921; Zelta Feike Rodenwold, 1921-1926; E.C. Allworth, 1926-1936; George T. Scott, 1936-1938; Warren Reid, 1938-1943; Eunice Courtright, 1943-1946; John Fenner, 1946-1948; Robert Knoll, 1948-1961; Crawford H. ("Scram") Graham, 1961-1978; Donald S. Wirth, 1978-1999; Stephen Smith, 1999-2000; Dwayne Foley, 2000-2004; and Jeffrey S. Todd, beginning in 2004.
The Alumni Association Records document the alumni of Oregon State University and the Association's administration and activities, and publications. The collection includes the records of individual graduating classes documenting activities during their student years as well as reunions and other special events after graduation. Lists of alumni and alumni directories are part of the collection. Subject files pertaining to notable alumni; faculty, staff, and friends of OSU; special events; and other university-related topics comprise a large component of the collection. The records of special events such as homecoming, class reunions, and the centennial of Oregon State University as well as fundraising for special projects such as a new football stadium and the carillon for the Memorial Union are included in the records. The collection includes extensive materials documenting the Association's publications - the alumni magazine, the Orange and Black, alumni directories, and sets of sound recordings of Oregon State songs. The collection also includes sound recordings by Bob Eberhard of Oregon State basketball games (in about 1957); a speech by Fred Shideler about the value of OSU to the Corvallis community; and an interview with Dan Poling about Corvallis and Oregon State College during World War II.
Collection is open for research.
The records are arrange in four subgroups: 1. Class Files, 1897-2002; 2. Administrative Files, 1914-2008; 3. Publications, 1929-2005; and 4. Microfilmed Records, 1888-1964.
Subgroup 1 (Class Files) consists of three series: I. Class Records, 1897-1966; Class Reunions, 1923-2002; and III. Alumni Register, June 1923 - June 1932.
Subgroup 2 (Administrative Files) consists of 17 series: I. Constitution and Bylaws, 1914-1990; II. Annual and Biennial Reports, 1938-1972; III. Board Meetings Records, 1941-1995; IV. OSU Federation Meeting Minutes, 1950-1976; V. Homecoming Records, 1948-1968; VI. Portland Information Center Files, 1945-1952; VII. School Songs, 1922-1952; VIII. Special Projects, 1945-1961; IX. OSU Centennial Celebration, 1965-1974; X. Alumni Leader's Manual, circa 1953; XI. OSU Fund, 1960-1978; XII. Correspondence, 1927-1975; XIII. Fiscal Records, 1926-1977; XIV. Sound Recordings, 1949-1991; XV. Scrapbook, 1950-1951; XVI. List of Alumni, undated; and XVII. Academy of Lifelong Learning, 2008.
Subgroup 3 (Publications) consists of four series: I. Alumni Magazine, 1929-1998; II. OSU Scope, 1966-1971; III. Orange and Black, 1938; IV. Alumni Directories, 1910-2005.
The microfilmed records (Subgroup 4) consist of 15 series: I. Class Reunion Files, 1891-1959; III. Reunion Weekends, 1939-1942; IV. Class Financial Records, 1924-1934; V. Reunion Lists, 1923-1925; VI. Reunion Letters, 1905; VII. Alumni Mailing List, 1935; VIII. Reunion Banquets, 1916-1946; XI. Alumni Association, 1942; XII. Class Lists, 1926-1945; XIII. Mailing Lists of Alumni, 1940-1941; XIV. Golden Jubilee Lists and Correspondence, 1888-1964; XV. Stadium Fund, 1951-1953; XVI. Correspondence, 1938-1953; XVIII. General Files, 1935-1950; and XIX. Memorial Chapel and Carillon Information, 1944-1959. There are no series II, IX, X, or XVII.
Transferred from the Alumni Association and the Alumni Relations Office in numerous accessions from the 1960s through 2008.
Additions to the collection are expected.
Additional photographs are available in the Alumni Association Photographs (P 017) and the Oregon Stater Photographs (P 195); motion picture films and videotapes are available in the Alumni Association Motion Picture Films and Videotapes (FV P 017). The OSU Archives includes many collections assembled and donated by individual alumni as well as the records of other alumni organizations such as the OSU Home Economics Alumni Association Records and the Oregon State University Women's Club Records. Materials pertaining to the Oregon State Forestry Alumni Association are part of the Les Lloyd Papers. The Academy for Lifelong Learning Records provide more detailed information about that affiliated organization.
The Oregon State Yank Collection documents the activities of Oregon State alumni during World War II.
The papers of several individuals who served as Director or Executive Secretary of the Association, edited the alumni magazine, or were significantly involved with alumni matters are part of the Archives' holdings: Edward C. Allworth, Chuck Boice, Ted Carlson, Crawford Henderson ("Scram") Graham, E.B. Lemon, and Edwin T. Reed. The George Edmonston Collection includes a variety of materials pertaining to OSU and regional history as well as his role as Editor of the Oregon Stater from 1986 until his retirement in 2005. The alumni magazine is available in the Archives as a separate collection; the Memorabilia Collection includes extensive materials about OSU alumni and a variety of ephemeral items documenting Alumni Association activities.
Edmonston, George P.; Poling, Dan Williams.; Shideler, Fred Merle.
Oregon Agricultural College--Alumni and alumnae.; Oregon State College--Alumni and alumnae.; Oregon State University--Alumni and alumnae.; Oregon State University--Alumni and alumnae--Periodicals.; Oregon State University--Centennial celebrations, etc.; Oregon State University--History.
Carillons--Oregon--Corvallis.; Class reunions--Oregon--Corvallis.; College environment--Oregon--Corvallis.; College sports--Oregon--Corvallis.; College students--Oregon--Corvallis.; Fund raising--Oregon--Corvallis.; Student activities--Oregon--Corvallis.; Students' songs--Oregon--Corvallis.; Universities and colleges--Alumni and alumnae--Oregon.; Universities and colleges--Public relations--Oregon.
Audiocassettes.; Audiotapes.; Compact discs.; Ephemera.; Film negatives.; Phonograph records.; Photographic prints.; Scrapbooks.
Colleges and Universities; Journalism; Music; Overland Journeys to the Northwestern United States; Publishers and Publishing; Sports and Recreation; Student Life; Oregon; Corvallis; Portland; Artifacts; Electronic Records; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sound Recordings
- Class Files, 1897-2002; Subgroup 1
  Subgroup 1, Class Files, document activities by class year before graduation and reunion events after graduation. They provide biographical information about alumni as well as document student activities, reunions, and special events.
  - Class Records, 1897-1966; Series I
    The Class Records include constitutions and bylaws, meeting minutes, class wills and prophesies, financial records, lists of members, and scrapbooks for individual classes from the Class of 1902 through the Class of 1967. The Class of 1922 records include eight lapel pins donated by Claude F. Palmer. Of special note are the two scrapbooks for the Class of 1902.
    - Class of 1902, 1897-1952
      - Minutes, 1898-1902 (Box 1)
      - Scrapbooks, 1897-1952 (Box 8)
        Two volumes assembled by Gertrude Ewing McElfresh include ephemera and memorabilia from student years of the Class of 1902 as well as reunions; clippings; lists of class members; obituaries; correspondence and 38 photographs. The photographs are primarily of reunion groups and activities and class members after graduation.
    - Class of 1910, circa 1908-1910
      - Minutes, 1908-1910 (Box 1)
      - Constitution, circa 1908 (Box 1)
      - List of class members (Box 1)
    - Class of 1911, 1907-1911
    - Class of 1912 Fiscal Ledger, 1909-1912 (Box 1)
    - Class of 1913
      - Constitution and By-Laws (Box 1)
      - Class Trip Expenses, 1913 (Box 1)
    - Class of 1914, 1910-1914
      - Minutes, 1910-1914 (Box 1)
        Also includes minutes from 5th, 25th and 40th class reunions.
      - Constitution and By-Laws (Box 1)
      - Class Prophecy (Box 1)
      - Class Will (Box 1)
    - Class of 1915 Minutes, 1911-1915 (Box 1)
    - Class of 1918, 1914-1918
      - Constitution and By-Laws (Box 1)
      - Minutes, 1914-1918 (Box 1)
      - Financial Reports (Box 1)
      - Class Elections Ballots (Box 1)
    - Class of 1919, 1915-1919
      - Constitution, 1916 (Box 1)
      - Class Will (Box 1)
      - Minutes, 1915-1919 (Box 1)
    - Class of 1920 Letter to Dean Bexell, November 20, 1919 (Box 1)
    - Class of 1922, 1919-1922
      - Minutes, 1919-1922 (Box 1)
      - Lapel Pins (Box 1)
        Pins have the following lettering, OAC, OAC Alumni, 22, and Orange Owl.
    - Class of 1924, 1919-1924
      - Minutes, 1920-1924 (Box 1)
      - Scrapbook Materials, 1919-1922 (Box 1)
        Mounted in Minutes Book.
      - Constitution (Box 1)
      - Artifacts from time capsule dug up in 1949, 1919-1922
        - Last Will and Prophecy of the Class of 1924 (Box 1)
        - Dance Program, June 7, 1924 (Box 1)
        - List of Graduates, 1924 (Box 1)
        - Contract between Class of 1924 and J. Leo Fairbanks for painting of mural (Box 1)
    - Class of 1925 Last Will and Testament, June 1925 (Box 1)
    - Class of 1926, 1922-1926
      - Cash Ledgers, 1922-1926 (Box 1)
      - Artifacts from time capsule dug up in 1951
        - Class Will (Box 1)
        - Class Prophecy (Box 1)
        - Commencement and Convocation Programs (Box 1)
    - Class of 1928, 1924-1928
      - Minutes, 1924-1928 (Box 1)
      - Class History, 1928 (Box 1)
    - Class of 1932 Bank Account Book, 1929-1932 (Box 1)
    - Class of 1933 Minutes, 1929-1933 (Box 1)
    - Class of 1934 Minutes, 1930-1934 (Box 1)
    - Class of 1936, 1932-1996
      - Minutes, 1932-1961 (Box 1)
      - Rosters and Reunions, 1981-1996 (Box 1)
    - Class of 1941, 1938-1941
      - Minutes, 1938-1941 (Box 1)
      - Account Book, 1941 (Box 1)
    - Class of 1942 Minutes, 1938-1942 (Box 1)
    - Class of 1944, 1940-1944
      - Minutes, 1940-1944 (Box 1)
      - Correspondence Class Funds, 1944 (Box 1)
    - Class of 1952 Scrapbook of Activities, 1948-1952 (Box 9)
      Clippings of activities of class members and other campus events; includes 9 photographs (portraits) of class members and officers.
    - Class of 1967 Scrapbook of Activities, 1966 (Box 10)
      Predominantly clippings and one photograph.
  - Class Reunions, 1923-2002; Series II
    Series II documents class reunions for the Class of 1888 through the Class of 1967. Most of the records pertain to reunions from the 1920s through 1970s. The records include correspondence, newspaper clippings, postcards, brochures, and photographs, primarily of reunion groups. These materials document the activities of Oregon State alumni after their graduation.
    - Class of 1888, 1926 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1889, 1925 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1890, 1925-1934 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1891, 1925-1941 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1892, 1925-1952 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1893, 1923-1943 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1894, 1923-1944 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1895, 1923-1945 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1896, 1923-1946 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1897, 1937-1947 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1898, 1923-1946 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1899, 1923-1949 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1900, 1923-1970 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1901, 1925-1951 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1902, 1926-1952 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1903, 1930-1953 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1904, 1926-1955 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1905, 1929-1955 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1906, 1925-1956 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1907, 1938-1959 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1908, 1924-1958 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1909, 1924-1969 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1910, 1924-1970 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1911, 1924-1970 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1912, 1923-1963 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1913, 1924-1973 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1914, 1923-1969 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1915, 1925-1966 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1916, 1937-1971 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1917, 1942-1967 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1918, 1923-1968 (Box 2)
    - Class of 1919, 1931-1969 (Box 3)
    - Class of 1920, 1937-1970 (Box 3)
    - Class of 1924, 1969 (Box 3)
    - Class of 1925, 1950 (Box 3)
    - Class of 1926, 1951 (Box 3)
    - Class of 1927, 1952 (Box 3)
    - Class of 1927, 1952-1987; 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Class of 1928, 1953 (Box 3)
    - Class of 1929, 1954-1969; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Class of 1938, 1939 (Box 3)
    - Class of 1967, 1977 (Box 3)
    - Golden Jubilee Records, 1941-1971 (Box 3)
    - Class of 1952 Golden Jubilee Reunion Memory Book, 2002 (Box 3)
      The book includes a program from the reunion, biographical information compiled from questionnaires completed by class members about their student activities and life after graduation, and a list of deceased class members.
    - Class Reunion Files, 1931-1996; 23 folders (Box 3)
      The files include photographs, brochures, newspaper clippings, and ribbons pertaining to class reunions. Files for the Classes of 1912-1916, 1918, 1921-1932, 1934-1937, 1939, and 1946 are included. Files include 350 photographs (prints and negatives), most of which are reunion groups
  - Alumni Register, June 1923-June 1932; Series III (Box 12)
    The Alumni Register served as a guestbook for alumni who visited campus and includes the date of their visit; name; class year and college; present occupation; home and business addresses; marriage date; number of children; and, for women, maiden name and husband's initials. The entries are chronological by date of visit.
- Administrative Files, 1914-2008; Subgroup 2
  The Administrative Files document the organization and management of the Association as well as major programs and activities including the annual homecoming events; special projects such as the carillon in the Memorial Union; commemoration of the Oregon State University centennial in 1968-1969; recordings of special events and Oregon State songs; and fundraising through the OSU Fund.
  - Constitution and Bylaws, 1914-1990; Series I (Box 3)
    Series I includes constitutions and bylaws for the Association dated 1914, 1934, 1941, and 1990.
  - Annual and Biennial Reports, 1938-1972; Series II (Box 3)
    The Annual and Biennial Reports include annual reports for 1938-1939 through 1941-1942 with related materials and a biennial report for 1970-1972.
  - Board Meetings Records, 1941-1995; Series III
    Series III consists of records of the Association Board of Directors, the Executive Committee, and other committees. The materials are from various years and do not represent a continuous or complete record.
    - Minutes, 1941-1942 (Box 3)
    - Committee Reports, March 2, 1951 (Box 3)
    - Board and Executive Committee Agendas and Minutes, 1977 (Box 3)
    - Meeting Minutes and Agendas, 1978 (Box 3)
    - Board and Executive Committee Meeting Materials, 1994-1995 (Box 3)
    - Board Member Directory for 1986-87 (Box 3)
    - Long Range Plan, 1986 (Box 3)
      Report of Long Range Planning Committee to the Board of Directors with draft proposal of long-range plan.
  - OSU Federation Meeting Minutes, 1950-1976; Series IV (Box 3)
    Series IV includes meeting minutes, draft constitution, correspondence, and related materials of the Federation, which was established in 1950 to coordinate, implement, and encourage activities of various members groups on behalf of Oregon State and its students. It includes representatives of the Mothers and Dads Clubs, the Alumni Association, the Associated Students (ASOSU), and Century Club.
  - Homecoming Records, 1948-1968; Series V
    The homecoming records consist of detailed annual reports of the homecoming weekend activities and programs that include clippings and ephemera. Scrapbooks documenting the 1961, 1962, and 1964 homecoming weekends are also included in the series.
    - Reports, 1948-1968
      - 1948-1961 (Box 3)
      - 1962-1968 (Box 4)
        Includes centennial homecoming in 1968.
    - Scrapbooks, 1961-1964
      - 1961-1962 (Box 11)
        Two volumes include primarily clippings with some ephemera, correspondence, and forms; no photographs.
      - 1964 (Box 10)
        Two identical scrapbooks with the same clippings; no photographs.
  - Portland Information Center Files, 1945-1952; Series VI
    Series VI consists of reports, correspondence, clippings, and ephemera documenting the Portland Information Center and its activities for current Oregon State student, prospective students, alumni, and friends. The Center participated in recruitment activities and provided information and activities to incoming students the summer before they enrolled at Oregon State.
    - Reports, 1945-1952 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1948-1949 (Box 4)
  - School Songs, 1922-1952; Series VII
    Series VII includes correspondence, clippings, and related materials pertaining to the alma mater, fight song, and other school songs. The clippings primarily document the publication of song books by the Alumni Association in the 1920s.
    - Correspondence on Status of Copyrights, 1936-1952 (Box 4)
    - General Correspondence, 1922-1942; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Clippings, 1922-1924 (Box 4)
  - Special Projects, 1945-1961; Series VIII
    Series VIII consists of materials documenting several special projects of the Alumni Association including fundraising for a new football stadium, proposals for a World War II memorial chapel, and materials pertaining to the carillon bell system in the Memorial Union, which was installed in 1959. This carillon was dismantled in the mid 1990s and replaced by a digital sound system.
    - Stadium Fund, 1950 (Box 4)
    - World War II Memorial Chapel, 1945-1954
      - Correspondence with other universities, 1947-1954 (Box 4)
      - Committee By-Laws and other organizing documents, 1949-1950 (Box 4)
      - Committee Correspondence, 1945-1950 (Box 4)
      - Publicity (Box 4)
    - Carillon, 1955-1976
      - Board of Directors File, 1955-1959 (Box 4)
      - Schulmerich Correspondence and Information, 1955-1959 (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1955-1959 (Box 4)
      - Money, 1955-1959 (Box 4)
      - Roberts, Thomas, letter, 1955-1959 (Box 4)
      - Spokane Trip, 1959 (Box 4)
      - Y Round Table, 1955 (Box 4)
      - Publicity, 1956-1959 (Box 4)
      - Notes, 1955-1959 (Box 4)
      - Carillonic Bell Music Rolls, 1959-1976 (Box 16)
        Four carollonic bell music rolls for hourly chimes at the Memorial Union. The rolls inclue the OSU fight song, "Hail to Old OSC", the alma mater, and secular and religious Christmas holiday selections. One of the rolls is a "word roll" with printed words to the alma mater and fight song.
      - Certificate, 1959 (Box 16)
        States that Schulmerich Carillons, Inc. installed a "3-octave, 86-bell Americana Carillon" in the Memorial Union on October 20, 1959.
  - OSU Centennial Celebration, 1965-1974; Series IX
    The Centennial Celebration records include agendas, minutes, and memoranda of the university-wide Centennial Committee as well as materials pertaining to selection of the Alumni Centennial Award recipients.
    - Centennial Committee, 1965-1974; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Alumni Centennial Award, 1968-1969 (Box 4)
  - Alumni Leader's Manual, circa 1953; Series X (Box 5)
    The Alumni Leader's Manual was prepared for the officers and representatives of the Association and includes the constitution and by-laws; policies and procedures; and information about the organization of the Association and its activities, programs, and services.
  - OSU Fund, 1960-1978; Series XI
    Series XI includes the first annual report of the Oregon State University Fund, which was established by the Alumni Association in 1959 to receive annual tax-deductible contributions from alumni and friends of OSU. The Comparison Report provides information about the number of donors and dollars received in 1976-1977 and 1977-1978.
    - Annual Report, 1960-1961 (Box 5)
    - Comparison Report, September 1978 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1927-1975; Series XII
    Series XII consists of several pieces of correspondence, primarily incoming, written by or about alumni. Some of the correspondence addresses positions of the Alumni Association on issues at Oregon State.
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1939-1975 (Box 5)
    - McKay, J.D., Letter to E.C. Allworth, 1927 (Box 5)
      Regarding the controversy between Oregon Agricultural College and the University of Oregon.
  - Fiscal Records, 1926-1977; Series XIII
    The Fiscal Records include a few items documenting the income of the organization in the 1920s and 1930s and the Association budgets in the mid-1970s.
    - Deposit Book, 1926-1930 (Box 5)
    - Saving Account Book, 1935-1938 (Box 5)
    - Insurance Policy, 1930 (Box 5)
    - Budget, 1976-1977 (Box 5)
  - Sound Recordings, 1949-1991; Series XIV
    The sound recordings include 18 vinyl sound disks, 12 reel-to-reel tapes, and 1 cassette tape. Of special note are recordings of the 1949 OSC vs University of Oregon football game; an OSC vs University or Oregon basketball game in about 1957; a speech by Fred Shideler; an interview with Dean of Men Emeritus Dan Poling in 1991 about Oregon State College and Corvallis during World War II; and two sets of recordings of Oregon State songs produced by the Alumni Association in the early 1950s.
    - Tape, Class of 1940, 1965? (Box 6)
      25th Reunion
    - Tape Interview, January 30, 1991 (Box 6)
      Interview with Dan Poling about Corvallis and Oregon State College during World War II by George Edmonston.
    - Recordings by Bob Eberhard, circa 1957
      Tapes (4) made by Bob Eberhard (Class of 1957) while student broadcaster on campus radio station.
      - Basketball games (Box 6)
        vs. Oregon and Univ. of Washington
      - Tau Kappa Epsilon pledges who stole "O" from Skinner's Butte in Eugene (Box 6)
      - Interview with campus spirit chairman (Box 6)
      - Heckart Lodge Trio (3 songs) (Box 6)